<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="troubleshooting">
   <title>Troubleshooting</title>

   <section id="ithinkihavefoundabug">
      <title>I think I have found a bug</title>

      <para>If you think you have found a bug you should verify this by posting to our forum first.</para>

      <para>Our forum is located at <ulink url="http://community.jboss.org/en/jbossas/jca">http://community.jboss.org/en/jbossas/jca</ulink></para>

      <para>You can also search our issue tracking system located at <ulink url="https://jira.jboss.org/jira/browse/JBJCA">https://jira.jboss.org/jira/browse/JBJCA</ulink></para>

   </section>

   <section id="iwouldliketoimplementafeature">
      <title>I would like to implement a feature</title>

      <para>So you have found an area where you are missing a feature and would like to submit a patch for it, great !</para>

      <para>There are a couple of steps to get a feature included</para>

      <para>First, you should create a new thread in our development forum where you describe the feature, its design and
        implementation.</para>

      <para>Once there is an agreement on the feature and the design you should proceed with creating the patch.</para>

      <para>To maximize your chances of getting the feature in the official build as soon as possible make sure that
        you run through the following steps:</para>

      <programlisting>
ant clean test
ant clean checkstyle
ant clean findbugs
ant clean cobertura
      </programlisting>

      <para>All these should show that,</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          All your test cases for the feature is passing
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Your code is correctly formatted according to project rules
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          There isn't any bug reports from the Findbugs environment
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          There is full code coverage based on the Cobertura report
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>when done, create a JIRA task (Patch) in our JIRA environment. See the developer guide for
        additional details.</para>

      <para>Happy Coding !</para>

   </section>

   <section id="howdoi">
      <title>How do I ?</title>

      <para>We can't cover every single issue in this guide, so feel free to drop by our forums to see if a solution
        has already been provided. Otherwise feel free to ask your question there.</para>

      <para>Our forum is located at <ulink url="http://community.jboss.org/en/jbossas/jca">http://community.jboss.org/en/jbossas/jca</ulink></para>

   </section>

   
</chapter>
