<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="eis">
   <title>EIS test server</title>

   <para>
     Testing an Enterprise Information System can be a complex task, as their installation
     can quite complex and specific to a certain platform architecture.
   </para>
   
   <para>
     As Java developers, and resource adapter developers in particularly, we are interested
     in a setup that will allow us to test the resource adapter against the EIS with as little
     difficulty as possible.
   </para>
   
   <para>
     Having access to a component that easy integrates into our testing environment, and
     acts as the EIS in question is of benefit.
   </para>
   
   <section id="eis_overview">
      <title>Overview</title>
   
      <para>
        The IronJacamar EIS test server provides a framework for emulating an Enterprise Information System
        such that no installation is needed.
      </para>
   
      <para>
        The EIS test server contains the following interface
      </para>

      <programlisting language="java">
<xi:include parse="text" href="../../../../eis/src/main/java/org/jboss/jca/test/eis/Handler.java" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
      </programlisting>

      <para>
        which represents a session between the resource adapter and the EIS.
      </para>

      <para>
        The <code>java.io.InputStream</code> is the incoming communication coming from the resource adapter, and
        the <code>java.io.OutputStream</code> is the EIS' response to the request.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Once the method returns the socket between the resource adapter and the EIS is closed.
      </para>

      <para>
        This means that the implementation of the <code>Handler</code> interface will represent the binary
        protocol between the resource adapter and the EIS. To the resource adapter it will look as it is
        communicating with the real Enterprise Information System installation.
      </para>

   </section>

   <section id="eis_ant">
      <title>Apache Ant</title>

      <para>
        The Apache Ant tasks for starting and stopping the EIS test server are defined as the following
      </para>

      <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
<taskdef name="start"
         classname="org.jboss.jca.test.eis.ant.Start"
         classpathref="main.lib.path.id"/>

<taskdef name="stop"
         classname="org.jboss.jca.test.eis.ant.Stop"
         classpathref="main.lib.path.id"/>
]]>
      </programlisting>

      <para>
        where <code>main.lib.path.id</code> contains the <code>ironjacamar-test-eis.jar</code> file.
      </para>

      <para>
        The <code>start</code> task is used, like
      </para>

      <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
<start host="localhost" port="1400"
       handler="org.jboss.jca.test.eis.EchoHandler">
  <classpath>
    <pathelement location="${build.eis.dir}/test"/>
  </classpath>
</start>
]]>
      </programlisting>

      <para>
        which starts the EIS test server on <code>localhost</code> using port <code>1400</code> with an
        implementation of the <code>Handler</code> interface of <code>org.jboss.jca.test.eis.EchoHandler</code>
        and a classpath of <code>${build.eis.dir}/test</code>.
      </para>

      <para>
        The <code>stop</code> task is used, like
      </para>

      <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
<stop host="localhost" port="1400"/>
]]>
      </programlisting>

      <para>
        which stops the EIS test server on <code>localhost</code> using port <code>1400</code>.
      </para>

      <para>
        Between the <code>start</code> and <code>stop</code> tasks the resource adapters unit tests
        can be executed.
      </para>
      
   </section>

   <section id="eis_maven">
      <title>Apache Maven</title>

   </section>

</chapter>
