<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<preface id="preface">
  <title>Preface</title>

  <section id="about">
    <title>About IronJacamar</title>

    <para>The goal of the IronJacamar project is to provide an implementation of the Java Connector
      Architecture 1.6 specification.</para>
    
    <para>The specification can be found here: <ulink url="http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=322">http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=322</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="whythename">
    <title>Why IronJacamar ?</title>

    <para>The Java EE Connector Architecture container can be viewed as a foundation inside an application server
      as it provides connectivity to the other containers such that they can communicate with EISes. Iron is often
      used as foundation in building houses too.</para>

    <para>The Jacamar bird family which lives in Central and South America are glossy elegant birds with long bills 
      and tails. Why we picked the Jacamar family is left as an exercise for the reader :)</para>

  </section>

  <section id="theteam">
    <title>The team</title>

    <para>Jesper Pedersen acts as the lead for the IronJacamar project. He can be reached at jesper (dot) pedersen (at) jboss (dot) org.</para>
    
    <para>Jeff Zhang is a core developer on the IronJacamar project. He can be reached at jizhang (at) redhat (dot) com.</para>

    <para>Stefano Maestri is a core developer on the IronJacamar project. He can be reached at stefano.maestri (at) redhat (dot) com.</para>

    <para>Gurkan Erdogdu is a core developer on the IronJacamar project. He can be reached at gurkanerdogdu (at) yahoo (dot) com.</para>

  </section>

  <section id="thanksto">
    <title>Thanks to</title>

    <para>
      Dimitris Andreadis, Carlo de Wolf, Jason Green, Jonathan Halliday, Søren Hilmer, Ales Justin, Vicky Kak,  
      Aslak Knutsen, Sacha Labourey, Alexey Loubyansky, Patrick MacDonald, Andrig Miller,
      Andrew Lee Rubinger, Anil Saldhana, Scott Stark and Jeremy Whiting.
    </para>
    
    <para>And a special thanks goes to Adrian Brock for his continuous support of this project.</para>

  </section>

  <section id="license">
    <title>License</title>

    <para>Copyright © 2010 Red Hat, Inc. and others.</para>
    <para>The text of and illustrations in this document are licensed by Red Hat under
      a Creative Commons Attribution–Share Alike 3.0 Unported license ("CC-BY-SA").</para>
    <para>An explanation of CC-BY-SA is available at 
      <ulink url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/</ulink>. 
      In accordance with CC-BY-SA, if you distribute this document or an adaptation
      of it, you must provide the URL for the original version.</para>
    <para>Red Hat, as the licensor of this document, waives the right to enforce, 
      and agrees not to assert, Section 4d of CC-BY-SA to the fullest extent 
      permitted by applicable law.</para>
    
  </section>

</preface>
