<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<preface id="preface">
  <title>Preface</title>

  <section id="about">
    <title>About IronJacamar</title>

    <para>The goal of the IronJacamar project is to provide an implementation of the Java Connector
      Architecture 1.6 specification.</para>
    
    <para>The specification can be found here: <ulink url="http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=322">http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=322</ulink>.</para>

    <para>The IronJacamar project is licensed under the GNU LESSER GENERAL PUBLIC LICENSE 2.1 (LGPL 2.1) license.</para>

  </section>

  <section id="whythename">
    <title>Why IronJacamar ?</title>

    <para>The Java EE Connector Architecture container can be viewed as a foundation inside an application server
      as it provides connectivity to the other containers such that they can communicate with EISes. Iron is often
      used as foundation in building houses too.</para>

    <para>The Jacamar bird family which lives in Central and South America are glossy elegant birds with long bills 
      and tails. Why we picked the Jacamar family is left as an exercise for the reader :)</para>

  </section>

  <section id="versions">
    <title>Versions</title>

    <para>
      This section contains the highlights of the IronJacamar releases. A full description of each release
      can be found through our issue tracking system at <ulink url="http://issues.jboss.org/browse/JBJCA">http://issues.jboss.org/browse/JBJCA</ulink>.
    </para>

    <section id="versions_ironjacamar10">
      <title>IronJacamar 1.0</title>

      <para>
        Highlights as compared to previous Java EE Connector Architecture containers inside JBoss Application Server:

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            Java EE Connector Architecture 1.6 certified (standalone / Java EE6)
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            POJO container environment
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            New configuration schemas which focuses on usability
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            Fast XML and annotation parsing for quick deployment
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            Reauthentication support
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            Prefill support for security backed domains
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            Support for pool flushing strategies
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            Embedded environment for ease of development with Arquillian and ShrinkWrap integration
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            New management and statistics integration for components
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            Code generator for resource adapters
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            Validator tool for resource adapters
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>

  </section>

  <section id="theteam">
    <title>The team</title>

    <para>Jesper Pedersen acts as the lead for the IronJacamar project. He can be reached at jesper (dot) pedersen (at) jboss (dot) org.</para>
    
    <para>Jeff Zhang is a core developer on the IronJacamar project. He can be reached at jizhang (at) redhat (dot) com.</para>

    <para>Stefano Maestri is a core developer on the IronJacamar project. He can be reached at stefano.maestri (at) redhat (dot) com.</para>

    <para>Lin Gao is a core developer on the IronJacamar project. He can be reached at lgao (at) redhat (dot) com.</para>

    <para>Vladimir Rastseluev is a core developer on the IronJacamar project. He can be reached at vrastsel (at) redhat (dot) com.</para>

  </section>

  <section id="thanksto">
    <title>Thanks to</title>

    <para>
      Dimitris Andreadis, Adrian Brock, Carlo de Wolf, Gurkan Erdogdu, Bruno Georges, Paul Gier, Jason Green, Stefan Guilhen, 
      Jonathan Halliday, Søren Hilmer, Ales Justin, Vicky Kak,  Aslak Knutsen, Sacha Labourey, Johnaton Lee, Mark Little, Alexey Loubyansky, 
      Patrick MacDonald, Scott Marlow, Shelly McGowan, Andrig Miller, Marcus Moyses, Weston Price, Andrew Lee Rubinger, Heiko Rupp,
      Anil Saldhana, Scott Stark, Clebert Suconic, Andy Taylor, Jeremy Whiting, Tyronne Wickramarathne and Yang Yong.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section id="license">
    <title>License</title>

    <para>Copyright © 2012 Red Hat, Inc. and others.</para>
    <para>The text of and illustrations in this document are licensed by Red Hat under
      a Creative Commons Attribution–Share Alike 3.0 Unported license ("CC-BY-SA").</para>
    <para>An explanation of CC-BY-SA is available at 
      <ulink url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/</ulink>. 
      In accordance with CC-BY-SA, if you distribute this document or an adaptation
      of it, you must provide the URL for the original version.</para>
    <para>Red Hat, as the licensor of this document, waives the right to enforce, 
      and agrees not to assert, Section 4d of CC-BY-SA to the fullest extent 
      permitted by applicable law.</para>
    
  </section>

</preface>
